Guide to the Frederick Kreiling Papers RG.012
Poly Archives at the Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology, NYU Libraries
Frederick Kreiling Papers
1962-2004
1962-1968
Poly Archives at the Bern Dibner Library of Science and Technology, NYU Libraries
Kreiling, Frederick C.
RG.012
12
0.5 Cubic Feet 1 box
The Frederick Kreiling Papers primarily consist of Kreiling's correspondence from 1964-1968. Kreiling (1923-2004) was a professor in the Humanities and Social Science (HuSS) department at Polytechnic from 1948 to 1992.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the Kreiling Papers consists of Frederick Kreiling's correspondence. Only one letter in the collection is not Kreiling's; it is from "Janice" to "Lenore". It is possible that Lenore is Kreiling's ex-wife.
The collection also includes biographical information about Kreiling, information about the History of Science program at Polytechnic, and annual reports from the NYC Department of Air Pollution.
Arrangement
The Kreiling Papers are arranged into two series: Correspondence and Miscellaneous. Correspondence is arranged chronologically. Items in the Miscellaneous series are also arranged chronologically, by subject.
Biographical / Historical
Frederick C. Kreiling was a professor in the Humanities and Social Sciences (HuSS) Department at Polytechnic from 1948 to 1992. He was first hired as a German instructor and transitioned into a history of science professor. In the fall of 1964, Kreiling was appointed head of the newly founded History of Science program at Polytechnic. In its first year, the program offered only three courses: Introduction to the History of Science, Topics in the History of Science, and Seminar in the History of Science.
Kreiling joined Polytechnic soon after serving in WWII as a German translator for POWs. During his career at Poly, his main research focus was on Gottfried W. Leibniz, an 18th-century German philosopher and mathematician. Besides teaching courses in the history of science, he also taught a course on the history of jazz. An accomplished bass player, Krieling played with the likes of Roy Eldridge, Coleman Hawkins, and John Lewis.
Kreiling retired from Polytechnic in 1992 and died on February 29, 2004.
Sources: "ePoly Briefs Home." 2013. Accessed April 24. http://www.poly.edu/poly_ebriefs/archives/April04.htm#PROFESSOR%20EMERITUS%20KREILING%20DIES.
1964. Polytechnic Reporter, October 1.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research without restrictions.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
This collection was donated in 2013 by Thomas B. Settle, former Professor of History in the Humanities and Social Sciences department and Professor Emeritus of the Technology, Culture, and Society department at Polytechnic.
Social Sciences; Correspondence; Polytechnic University (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.) -- Department of Social Sciences; Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn
- Correspondence, 1962-1968; 5976
  - Frederick Kreiling, 1964-1968; 5977
    - Correspondence, 1968, 5978 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence, 1967, 5979 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Correspondence, 1966 June - December, 5980 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Correspondence, 1966 February - May, 5981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Correspondence, 1965, 5982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Correspondence, 1964, 5983 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Lenore, 1962; 5984
    - Correspondence, 1962, 5985 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Miscellaneous, 1962-2004; 1962-1965; 5993
  - Graduate Level Program in History of Science Brochures and Enrollment Cards, 1965, 5994 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Annual Reports of the Department of Air Pollution, City of New Yorkm 1962-1963, 5995 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Biographical Information, 2004, 5996 (Box 1, Folder 10)